Cloud Sonnet 5.5 is here and it is a
clear upgrade over Claude Sonnet 5.
Running 30% faster as well as costing
30% less for most work. So, I've been
playing around with it all day on my
actual real workflows. Things like
building websites, taking a bunch of
messy data and turning that into
spreadsheets. Also, Excel sheets with
different views as well as formulas
inside of every single cell, motion
design and editing videos, interactive
dashboards that have real-time data
syncing, project management and
planning, and so many other things as
well. But specifically, I've been
testing Son of 5.5 against Opus 5.5, so
you know exactly when you should be
using which model. Now, in all these
comparisons, I'll go over how fast they
are, the input and output tokens, and
how much they actually cost you in
dollars. So, let's not waste any time
and just get straight into this one.
Okay, so before we jump into all of the
different demos, I just wanted to lay a
foundation here, which is how much does
Sonnet 5.5 actually cost versus Opus
5.5? The answer is roughly half. So here
you can see Sonnet 5.5 is $2 per million
input tokens whereas Opus is four and
Sonnet is $10 for the million output
tokens whereas Opus 5.5 is 20. So Opus
is roughly double the cost of Sonnet
5.5. So we're here to see if Opus is
double the quality of Sonet 5.5 and
where to use each model because Claude
actually came out themselves and dropped
this little guide that said, "Hey,
here's when you should use each model.
If you have something well scoped for
everyday coding, fixing bugs, sonnet it
high volume everyday development,
sonnet. polished documents, slides,
spreadsheets, one pagers, sonnet. You
should basically be using Opus if it's
complex work requiring careful judgment,
including long horizon, agentic coding,
and knowledge work. And for your hardest
problems where you need the most
intelligence, opus 5.5. I really like
this section down here. Sonnet 5.5 fits
best when the task has a clear spec and
a way to check the result. And so, the
way that I interpret this is basically
if you have a task with an objective
definition of done, then try that out
with Sonnet 5.5 first. If you need some
more creativity and you're looking for a
thought partner to help you decide what
the definition of done is and it's a bit
more subjective, then that's where I
would use opus as my model of choice for
that task. And then what I'd do is I'd
run different skills with different
models and I'd see, okay, for this
skill, Sonnet does better. For this
skill, Opus does better. So in the
future when I want to run this skill
again, I know which model to use.
Anyways, you guys know the drill here. I
gave all of these different sessions the
exact same prompt. And now we will be
reviewing the results. I did Sonnet 5.5
and Opus 5.5 both on high. When it comes
to the actual effort level, they both
used high. So the first thing was
building a engaging and immersive but
high converting landing page for perk
form. And I said that they could use
key.ai to generate anything they need.
And you can see I had to correct it
key.ai, not G.AI. So I should actually
probably add that as a misspelling
inside of my glido to correct this to
key. Okay, cool. All right, so let's
take a look at these two outputs. I'm
not going to tell you which one was
which until the end. I really like how
when this one loads up, we have that
text come in. Really cool. We can see
that this can is interactive. It syncs
to what my mouse is doing. Right off the
bat, I noticed that this can is kind of
a 3D rendering. So, it's not actually
the exact can like pixel for pixel the
way it should be. So, it had to kind of
invent that. I don't love that. But, I
do like the effect that it gave for us.
I also like how in the back you can see
Oh, wow. Actually, if I click and drag
it like scrolls the can, but you can see
in the background we can see like perk
form. We can see text in the back, which
I thought was pretty cool. Anyways,
let's go ahead and scroll down. We can
see the different flavors here. We can
actually switch right from the hero
section, which is pretty neat. As we
scroll down, we get the can flooding
away. And then we have two drinks,
coffee, and protein coming into one,
which gives us our one can, which is our
perk form. We can see we scroll down
into a little section where we have a
gym bag, phone, keys, and as we scroll,
we have the time going up, and now we
grab our perk form. We have a little
flavor section. So, we have the three
different flavors. I'm able to see that
I can click between them here. So, we
have our salted caramel, we have our
vanilla latte, we have our bold mocha.
It's sort of starting to tell a little
bit of a story here. And then that is
basically the end. And we have these
three dynamic cans coming back into
view. Okay. So, that was one output.
Here is the other one. So, right off the
bat, this one isn't as like boom right
in your face. It's not as much wow
factor, I'd say. We do have sort of an
element where it's syncing to the mouse.
You can see as I'm moving, you can see
these are on different layers. Also, the
key is on a different layer over here.
And I think that honestly this looks a
little bit cheaper when we look at just
kind of like the hero section. But as we
scroll, we can see that those other two
drinks kind of come down here. It's
doing a similar style where we're like
scrolling through a time. And I don't
love this one as much. It's kind of
making all of your eyes and all of your
attention go to one spot. So it's
definitely telling a different style of
story here. Even though all the branding
and everything else is consistent, this
is using the actual real generated image
inside of the brand guidelines for the
product. So, that is better that it gave
us the actual um I guess image in a real
way rather than back here if you guys
remember it was like a generated
version. Here's a cool little animation
here. We zoom into that image. All of
these were different independently
generated images. I think that this
looks really nice. Ultimately, this is
the better output in my mind. The one
thing I don't like as much is this
section. I think that this version tells
a little bit of a better story, but
ultimately this is the better output.
Even though I don't like the hero
section as much, this is the better
output. So, this one was Opus 5.5 and
this one was Sonet. I think Sonic killed
the hero section. If this would have
been a real CAN and then Opus 5.5 missed
that, but everything else of Opus'
version I think was better. So, if we
look at the stats here, we can see that
Sonnet ran for 28 minutes whereas Opus
ran for 52 minutes. Sonnet cost 20
million input tokens, 134K output
tokens. Opus was 37 million and 148k
output. and Opus cost about double here.
So Opus ran for about twice as long and
cost about twice as much, which is
pretty consistent with what we saw when
we actually look at the pricing. The
question to me now would be, is Opus'
output two times better? I would say no.
So ultimately, what I would probably
want to do here is I would reprompt
Sonnet and say, "Hey, this is really
good, but don't use like this fake
image. Use our actual real images." And
I bet that it could swap everything out.
And then I bet that it could give us the
level of output we were looking for with
a real can and it wouldn't have costed
us $13. So ultimately that's why I think
that we need to give this run, we give
the win here to Sonnet. But either way,
this stuff is subjective. So take it as
you will. But that is what we're going
to do right now is I'm going to give
this first output to Sonnet. And in my
latest videos, you guys have been saying
like, "Oh, please can you use the
subscription um usage instead of the API
billing?" No, I think this is a better
way to show the actual cost. These costs
are very much correlated to your
subscription. So, just think about it
like that. But the reason I'm not going
to do subscription is because I don't
know if you're on the 20 bucks a month
plan or the 200 bucks a month plan. I
also like to run all of these in
parallel and I don't want to like sit
and wait 52 minutes and then jot down
what percent it was and then do this one
for 28 minutes and then jot like, you
know, I'm just gonna run this in
parallel. Anyways, let's move on to
number two. Real quick, guys, I've got
this completely free website design
skill that I'm giving away. I use this
for every single website that I build,
including our AI Automation Society
site, which I think is pretty slick, and
I absolutely love this website. It's
called ScrollCraft, and it understands
things like scroll driven animations,
and layering, but also it has things in
there like taste, typography, spacing,
depth. It's just a really good website
design skill in general, and it's
completely free. So, the link for this
will be down in the description, but
let's get back to the video. All right,
for number two, what I did is I said,
"Hey, I need you to make me a motion
showre skill about glido." and you do
the research, make sure that all of this
is consistent in branding, typography,
you know, all of this kind of stuff. You
are the motion designer here. So, just
impress me. So, let's first look at
Sonnet's output.
Refactor this function to use uh async
await instead of promises.
I will fold those into the next
revision. Reply saying it looks good and
we can start next week.
We try logic to the API client.
Okay, really not bad at all. I thought
there was a lot of creativity here where
it's kind of showing off what the
product actually looks like when you use
it, which I thought was really nice. The
voice over that it did, it generated
that with maybe 11 Labs or something. I
also really liked how these pixels here
formed a G and that actually turned into
an AI generated video that it made. So,
I thought that was pretty nice. Overall,
I was honestly not expecting a Sonnet
model to do this good with this motion
show reel. Now, let's go take a look at
Opus' output.
Refactor this function to use async
await instead of promises.
Okay. I mean, I don't think you can beat
that. Opus 5.5 is just so good as of now
at motion design. It just felt more
glido. the background, the different
animations it made, it just felt like
even the copy was better. It also went
to our website and pulled this quote
from me that was on the site, which was
very fast. But right here, this was
actually the quote from the website. So
ultimately, this output much better from
Opus. Now, when we look at the cost
here, Opus was faster and it was also
less output tokens, but ultimately it
was more expensive. So, Sonnet was
$14.37 whereas Opus was $2055.
I think though we're gonna give this one
to Opus. If I'm still looking through
the lens of if we had Sonnet try again
to get up to $20.5,
I still think Opus' would be a better
output. It just had a better taste with
like motion and the sound design. And
sound design is something that I think
is really hard to get right even as a
human sometimes. And the fact that Opus
is doing this so consistently, very
good. So, I'm giving this one to Opus.
Okay, so for number three, I said very,
very vague. create me a researchbacked
90-day action plan for getting how they
AI to a thousand subscribers. So, let's
go first take a look at Sonnet's output.
Okay, so one thing to call out here is
both of these models originally when I
shot off that prompt, they just gave me
a markdown file. And then for both of
them, I gave them the exact same second
prompt, which was turn that into some
sort of document that I can view that's
easier for me to read. And this is
Sonnet's version. It created me an HTML
file and it gave it to me locally. And
then Opus did the same thing except for
it put it as a clawed artifact. So,
that's one little tiny difference, but
besides that, this is Sonnet's output.
Let's see. 1,000 subscribers in 90 days.
It also threw our logo up here, AIS
Media, September 28th. We have day one
launch as well as the day 90 goal. It's
interesting that it chose to launch this
on November 2nd rather than like next
month or something, Q4. Anyways, we have
a timeline here. So, we have episodes on
the bottom. We have subscriber gates and
getting to a,000 by day 90. We can see
that we have some other things here like
promotions. Test send full list full
list. We have Nate promotion sends out
six of them. Community posts five of
them. 500 subs. Holidays locked.
Interesting. We have different phases.
So what to do from October to November
and then two weeks on launch and then a
month in the next stage and then
compounding. So it's showing us the
different sort of milestones to hit in
these different phases. It's showing us
the different sources that we can get
subscribers from. None of this is
interactive. doesn't look like. It's
just showing us what this could look
like. We can also see that we got some
scroll animations coming in there, which
I thought was a nice touch. As you can
see, the text comes in. It's also
looking at shorts and LinkedIn and guest
kit and scorecards and other decisions
like that. Okay, so this is good. I
wouldn't say that this is like super
super helpful for me at the moment, but
not too bad. And here we have the
version with also scroll animations from
Opus as a cloud artifact. This one chose
to start October 1st to December 29th.
So, it's actually like a Q4 90-day
sprint, which I think is a bit more
aligned based on like what's going on in
our business right now. So, now we have
the 90 days. This one gave us a little
bit of a different sort of view, which I
actually like better. I'd say we can see
when we're going to launch. And from now
until launch, we'd be kind of setting up
auditions and we'd be doing guest
applications and we'd be, you know,
announcing all of this kind of stuff,
recording these episodes. we'd be
looking at getting out shorts and
hitting the email list and community
posts and all this kind of stuff. I
think that this view is a little bit
easier to digest than what's going on
here. They're just a bit too much going
on here and it's not as clear. Whereas
this seems a little bit more clear to
me. We have different phases here, but
this one's basically each month, which I
think is better. Build, launch,
compound. Same thing. Where do these
actual subscribers come from? The list,
YouTube organic, Nate's channel, things
like that. Here are things that we
actually need to decide on. And then we
can open the full plan which actually
takes us to oh wow this takes us to like
an actual very specific write up with
like tasks. So this is basically
something that I could throw into my
OTAA now. And we have these actual tasks
that we can check off. Okay, I think
this one's pretty clear. Opus wins this
test. Now when we take a look at the
stats, Opus ran for 20 minutes. Sonnet
ran for 14. Sonnet cost a little under
$5, whereas Opus costs a little over $9.
So, if we had Sonnet take another stab
at it, where would Sonnet be? Now, this
one gets really interesting to me
because if you think about the actual
prompt, I didn't really give it
guidelines at all. I said, "Create me a
researchbacked 90-day action plan." That
was it. And if we think about what I
said earlier, if you have an objective
definition of done, use Sonnet. If you
need more creativity and you're looking
for a thought partner, use Opus. And
this is definitely an example of me
looking for a thought partner and
looking for a model to just take a
ambitious goal or sort of a vague goal
and just run with it. I think that if I
would have given both of these models a
very very specific prompt on here's what
I want, here's how it should look,
here's blah blah blah, I think that opus
and sonnet would have given me a similar
result but sonnets would have been
cheaper. So I do really think that
that's interesting to think about the
way that you talk to these different
large language models. But in this case
I can't ignore how much better opus did
with this vague prompt even with the
cost. So, this one is going to go to
Opus as well. So, right now we're at
Opus is winning two to one. And really,
guys, I'm not trying to come in here and
say like which model is better than
which because ultimately Opus is a
better model, but I'm just trying to
hopefully show you guys like now you
might have a better idea of when to use
each model and or how to use each model.
So, let's hop into number four. All
right. So, in this one, I gave them a
bunch of company data, mock company
data, and I wanted to get an Excel sheet
as well as a investor pitch deck. So,
we're going to do Opus first. Here is
the deck that Opus built. It generated
this image in the back. We've got 18
slides. We've got generated images here
as well. We have the problem. We have
the product. We have who we serve. We
have some traction, so some statistics
in here based on the mock data. We've
got the business model, customers. Now,
this doesn't look too bad. We've got
visuals. We've got, you know, not too
much going on on each slide, but I will
say this is the infamous clawed design
font with the Fs like that and the
numbers. It doesn't look super premium
in my mind. Like this doesn't feel as
premium as I'd like it to, but either
way, the slides aren't designed super
super poorly or anything. So, that is
the output. I mean, this really isn't
bad at all from Opus 5.5. And then on
the Excel sheet, we have a dashboard,
inputs, monthly metrics, we have
different views. The dashboard is really
nice with all these stats and all of
these different visualizations in here.
We have the different inputs. We have
metrics, quarterly, P&L. What I really
like is in a lot of these cells, we see
formulas. We see formulas basically
everywhere. Which means if we had to
come in here and change up the data, the
whole sheet would update. I don't like
when AI models will give you a Excel
sheet with no formulas and now you have
to basically it's all static. It's all
hard-coded data and if you needed to
make changes, you would have to go ask
the agent to make those changes for you.
I hate when it does that. So, it's
really good that Opus is putting I mean
there's tons and tons of slides here,
like a ton of slides or sheets, I guess,
tabs. What I like is that they have
formulas inside. So, it's really not bad
at all from Opus. We've even got some
color coding and stuff. Very good Excel
sheet. This is interesting because if
you guys remember earlier, Opus made an
artifact and Sonnet didn't. But in this
time, Sonnet made an artifact. So, let's
see how this one's looking. This is
Bright Path Analytics. We see our intro
right there. We have I believe this is
the exact same font that Opus was using.
So anyways, we have um company snapshot,
the problem, the product, who we serve,
business model, traction. I mean, this
is very very similar. Like there's not
really any difference in my mind between
the two different decks. They feel and
look very very similar and sonnet
actually gave us more slides. Now, let's
open up the Excel sheet we got from
Sonnet. Immediately, it doesn't look as
premium, but we go into the dashboard.
The dashboard looks just fine. We have a
lot of visualizations here. monthly
data. We can see that we have lots of
formulas in these calculation cells.
Same thing with the P&L. We have some
SAS metrics. We have assumptions. We
have organic forecast. All of these are
different lookups and formulas as well.
Wow. Lots of different tabs here.
Pipeline, customers, marketing,
headcount. So, this one honestly might
have given us like too much. I don't
know. If this was real data and this was
my real company, I'd be able to tell you
guys better like how useful all this is.
But ultimately, I wouldn't really be
able to come in here and say that one of
these outputs doing this sort of like
document creation was significantly
better than one of the other AI models.
So, I really think in this case,
whichever model was cheaper and faster
is who I'm going to say won this round.
And wow, in this case, Opus was actually
cheaper and faster. So, we don't even
have to discuss this one. Opus wins this
one. No question. Cheaper, faster, and
the outputs were pretty much identical
in my mind. Now, what if we had some
skills built around it? That would be
another interesting thing to test. But
in this case, I didn't utilize a skill.
I just said, "Hey, make these things for
me." All right. So, here's an example
where it actually did use a skill. I
have a skill called HTML explainer, and
I asked it to use that skill or I didn't
ask it to, but it did. Where I said,
"Hey, what models could I run on my
current device? I don't know anything
about this, so make it easy to
understand. Lots of pictures, blah,
blah, blah." So, let's take a look at
these outputs. All right, so this one is
Opus. What AI can my PC run? You can see
this is branded. It's just a super
simple, you know, HTML explainer style
skill that I use sometimes. So, we can
see we have graphics card, memory,
processor, storage. We see the graphics
card memory versus other things, which
is like a gaming PC at a data center
chip. The 32 GB rule. The model has to
fit in your graphics card. So, we
probably couldn't run this 43 GB model,
but we could run a 20 GB model. So, that
is a nice little simple rule. We can see
that we also have shunk copies. We have
speed, so tokens per second on our
graphics card. What to install? Everyday
chat. It gives us a suggestion. Coding
hard problems. Gemma 4 for fast replies.
Super super cool. Too big for one PC.
Start tonight. It tells us exactly what
we would need to do. Okay, cool. Very
simple. Not too bad at all. Okay. And
now we have the exact same skill, exact
same prompt, but this is the sonnet
version. So, local AI models your PC can
run. It actually made us a little
visual, which I thought was cool. 32 GB,
the number that decides what local
means. Okay, so it starts off with what
local means, which I don't think the
other one did. The other one basically
just went straight into RPC. So that's
good that it did that. It broke it down
simply with another little
visualization. Three places to keep
model desk, shelf, warehouse. Okay.
Fast, slow, storage only. What fits?
Green fits, amber crawls, red won't run.
So it doesn't exactly tell me why
because of the whole gigabytes thing,
but it does show a nice little
visualization and some other AI models.
So that's not too bad. It also shows us
speed, pick by the job, similar to the
last one, and how to actually try one
out right now. So ultimately, if we
really think about how would we want to
understand how this stuff works, I do
think that Opus' output was better. Like
this one is more visual, I'd say, but it
doesn't actually explain it to me as
well as the Opus one did, unfortunately.
So I would say that Opus wins this
output. But if we think about this cost
here, similar timing, Sonnet cost half
of what Opus cost. So, if I prompted
Sonnet one more time and said, "Hey, I
am still confused about this, this, and
this. Can you just add some more info
here?" I bet that Sonnet's output would
be better. And I would also argue that I
think that Sonnet's output visually is
better. And that's one of the the pieces
of this skill, which is a very, very
simple skill. It's not refined at all,
but ultimately, I think that if we
prompted Sonnet again, we would get an
output better than what Opus gave us for
$3. So, I'm going to give this one to
Sonnet. Okay. So, in this next one,
number six, I said, "Scrape X for all
the news that's been going on today.
Give me an interactive dashboard so I
can view what's going on and see what's
coming out and just get prepped for all
these different things going on in the
AI space." So, let's take a look at
Sonnet's output. This is a local host
that it created from me. We can see that
we can see when this was last scraped.
We can hit refresh. We can see how many
posts were tracked. So, 386 posts
tracked from 676 scraped. We can see
some headline news right up top. We can
see what is trending. We can mark fits
my channel or hide covered or pinned
only. Okay, interesting. We can also see
the heat score. So, Claude Sonet 5.5 100
heat metastarts meta enterprise platform
94 heat. We can maybe click into this
stuff. Nope, I can just hover over. I
can open details. Okay, cool. So, I can
actually open the actual post that it's
sourcing, which is pretty nice. We can
mark it covered. We can add to plan. So,
now we get this list with like a content
plan over there. Not too bad. We can
also sort by newest. We can sort by
channel fit. We can look at the last 48
hours. We can see what's coming this
week, dev day by OpenAI. We can see the
calendar. Okay, this is not a bad view
at all. And now here we have Opus'
version, which off the bat just kind of
looks a little bit better to me. You can
see that this one's still scraping X. As
you can see, it's showing us a little
progress bar. So, it is working, but
this view looks a little bit more
visual. It's showing us posts per hour
on AI. It's showing us how many posts
are rising and cooling off. And this
view, in my opinion, is just a little
bit better. I can also switch up here
this week. Okay, nice little view here.
We can see content plan, so I can add
things to my list. We can see the raw
feed as well. So, that's pretty cool. I
can see sort of a heat score as well.
It's tagging things by rumor or shipped
or discussion. And it's pulling up real
posts on the side here. And let's see,
how do I add something to right there? I
can click add to content plan. I can
open the top post and it goes to X.
Okay, very cool. So, I'm really starting
to understand a pattern here, which is
what I said at the beginning. If you
know exactly what you want, Sonnet is
probably going to be able to do a good
job for you. But if you need the
creativity and you send an open-ended,
very vague goal, Opus is just going to
handle it better. And that's become
very, very clear to me. In this case,
Opus ran for about 7 minutes longer and
cost $6 more. And if we iterated four
more times with Sonnet, or as much as it
took to get to $8 of output, but we had
a clearer goal, then Sonnet would
definitely give us that level of output.
There's nothing in here that Sonnet
would have not been able to code or
create for us. It's just that Sonnet
doesn't think about that as much and it
won't go kind of like outside the box as
much as Opus will to give you a better
experience. It's basically just going to
give you what it thinks you want and
it's going to be the the baseline. So,
if we're sticking with my rule here,
because Sonnet was much cheaper, I'm
going to give this one to Sonnet. But
ultimately, like right now on one
prompt, Opus' output was better there
and there's just no denying that. So,
let's go on to the last one, number
seven. All right. So, in this one, I
gave Opus and Sonnet a link to one of my
YouTube videos and I said, "Create me a
YouTube resource guide." So, this is
using a skill once again. So, the skill
is defining what good looks like
essentially. So, let's take a look at
Sonnet's output. First, we have the AIS
header up top. We have this font. We
have Nate Herk linking to my YouTube
channel. It starts off with the
challenge and the rules. It goes over
the S&P benchmark. It goes over the
actual steps of how I built this. We
have the problem, the solution, day one
and day two results, day three, day
four, day five, day six, day seven,
final results, lessons learned, and we
have key takeaways down here. They're
pretty much the exact same length. This
one is like seven pages, but it's really
like I don't know, there's a big gap
here, whereas this one, very similar.
Same link, same title, same header, the
overview, the rules, the benchmark, how
the system was built, um day one, day
two, final results, all this kind of
stuff. It's very very similar, which is
why this one would be essentially
whichever one was cheaper is the one
that I would go with here. In this case,
you can see that Sonnet was cheaper and
faster about half the speed. So twice as
fast and a dollar40
cheaper. So this one is going to go to
Sonnet because the outputs were not too
different enough to actually beble to
say, "Oh, one's really better than the
other." And it's because in this case, I
know we've seen some other examples
where it didn't always match, but in
this case, I had a skill that I do use a
lot. And a model like Sonnet that's less
intelligent than Opus was able to just
follow my instructions because it knew
what I wanted more clearly. So, this one
goes to Sonnet. So, ultimately in this
test, we had three, four go to Sonnet
and three go to Opus. So, we did
technically have Sonnet winning this
challenge, but I think you guys
understand this wasn't really a
head-to-head. It was more like how and
when to use each model. And here are the
final stats for you guys. You can see
across these seven sessions, Opus ran
for about 46 minutes longer. It spent
about 38 million input tokens more as
well as actually less output tokens,
which is interesting. But it did cost
about $16 more than Sonnet 5.5 in all
these runs, which when you think about
the fact that it's actually double the
cost of Sonnet, it didn't cost double
the cost in this experiment, which is
also interesting. I've talked a lot
about how I see each of these models
fitting into my workflow now. And
hopefully you guys have a better idea of
how this all should work for you. But
ultimately, you got to get in there and
you got to test it on your own skills
and your own prompts and your own
processes. So, that's going to do it for
this one. That was my experiment today.
I hope you guys enjoyed. I hope you
learned something new. And if you did,
please give it a like. It helps me out a
ton. And as always, I appreciate you
guys making it to the end of the video.
I'll see you on the next one. Thanks,
everyone.